[Music]
y think too small I got Big Dreams you
just starting them way ahead at the end
scenes started reading and dodging all
the quick sches money like your
[Music]
Spotify hi I'm Daniel I'm Sarah and this
is episode 17 of the dealmakers podcast
where we talk about deals that fail to
close or struggle to close and help you
learn lessons from other people's
struggles and failures so you can avoid
them yourself and learn to look out for
certain red flags and our guest today is
Daniel
talit yes so as you know I am I I think
I can actually say it now I am fully a
business broker I'm not taking on any
more accounting clients uh you know
helping accounting firms and people buy
accounting firms but focusing on m&a
advisory and as a business broker so
that's like official as of last week
they doing all the m&a advisory for lots
of different um industry types as well
which is more interesting than my
stories because my stories are all like
accounting accounting accounting but
you've got one from this week about a
clothing boutique which is a real thing
that you can walk into and touch
things and women's clothing no less in a
very affluent area I stand out when I
visit um but it is is fun no I I love it
I love entrepreneurship I love small
business so much and I would never own a
women's clothing boutique or I would
have never thought to I would now it's
like crazy profitable but um or are you
just saying that because you're trying
to sell one right now no no no like I
don't know that they all are but this
one is this one's insane really um I
just oh I just got the updated
financials and half of the year she's
they're already at $300,000 net with no
like I without adjustments like that's
just the straight up net income wow yeah
okay and how much is gross like to give
context are you having to
spend oh wow yeah yeah their gross last
year was 1.2 with 300 and that like with
ADB backs it was like conservatively 350
maybe maybe towards 400 you know some
other things that were done that I'm
Gonna Keep if somebody's interested
reach out you'll get to get the whole
scoop but um you know you know
aggressively we could do 400 SD
conservatively it was like 350 and that
was for the whole year so like while
everybody is struggling in this election
year this business is thriving there's a
lot of specifics to that right because
it's not I mean it's not like all
clothing boutiques are created equal I'd
imagine so being in like an affluent
neighborhood um probably you're just G
to get more you're in Florida yeah and
so generally speaking I I uh I live in
Vero Beach um The Firm the business is
listed online you can find it on
business byell so I'm not sharing
anything that's confidential um but I
live in ver Beach Vero Beach is an
interesting Market because it's a a very
prominent retirement area for corporate
Executives coming out of New England so
like coming from New Jersey New York a
lot of people settle here and so we have
a Barrier Island and the Barrier island
is very affluent um you know it's a a
lot of big names A lot of people live
over there have houses over there and
this particular business is on
Ocean Drive so it's like 50 feet from
the beach and it's it's in like the
central part of Ocean Drive it's like
prime prime prime real estate and they
sell high-end stuff so it's there's a
lot of nuances to this like it's not
just like a random women's clothing
boutique and you know somewhere
strange yeah
and there's factors to this that make it
that lend to the profitability of the
business here's a question I always
wonder when I see a genuinely good
business business listed is why is the
person selling if it's retirement ah so
are do you think that it's like because
shopping online I don't know if you've
heard about it you can buy things on the
internet and they'll just ship them
straight to you um so you know do you
think that that's disruptive do you
think that um maybe because the it
sounds like maybe the population skew is
older that it's more attractive I think
that there's like a built-in mode
for this particular type of business
because the lines that are sold aren't
lines that like like when I heard the
names I wasn't like oh I've seen that at
Macy's like these are smaller lines that
they carry that are wanted by people who
live in and frequent Nantucket Martha's
Vineyard and like the boutiques in those
places so they like they kind of have
like a certain taste that they're
looking for and there's a certain style
that's sold in those places and then
when they come down here for the winters
they get their like kind of resort
tropical version of like these smaller
names so it's like more of like an
exclusivity so I'm not saying you can't
find these clothes online but like
you're not going to find them on Amazon
got it it's not like your te- orders
yeah show up in the big bag I've heard I
don't know yeah but what was so
surprising to me is like I've I've hung
out over there a couple times cuz like
there's some great places to get a
coffee or you know to get a drink or
something so like kind of not like
hanging out in the store it's a small
store like hanging out out front chair
they keep out of the fitting room just
like yeah just like post it
up um no but it's like it's I've noticed
it's an experience and when I when I
listed it I was like okay this is going
to be older affluent women that are
shopping here but I've actually seen a
number of young girls like in their
their teens that you know are like
excited to go in they're looking at the
clothes I know there was one that was
like oh this is where I found the dress
I want mom come in like let's go so it's
like it's like kind of part of the
shopping experience when you're
traveling here and a lot of people do
travel here to visit their grandparents
that live here grandparents want to take
kids shopping that's like a thing do yes
so it's like more of an experience
because there a metric used in clothing
like price per unit or something where
you can kind of evaluate like these are
more expensive items or there there
probably is but one of the unique
qualities of of our area is that they're
there are plenty of people who are well
off that live on the mainland that go
over to the island for a variety of
things and then there are is a group of
people who are like snowbirds they come
in during winter so this store actually
Cycles the lines that they carry for
winter or summer they carry a completely
different uh series of clothing lines
during the summer that are at a lower
price point oh interesting so like at
any given time during the winter the
store is maintaining 100 to 150,000 in
inventory but during the summer it may
be like 50 to 70 so like it's a big
difference in what they carry
interesting okay there there's so much
pychology to um this type of thing and
just the buying process that I haven't
put a lot of thought into so what have
you learned through the deal process
okay so well before I get to the deal
like just even operating the business
Florida is a weird place because we
don't have like a traditional winter we
have a series of cold fronts so like
even in December it could be Beach
weather it could be 70 Dees on Christmas
day but then the next day we could have
a cold front and it's 50 or 45 you know
so something that's so brilliant about
this business owner is she keeps her
winter stuff so that like if there's a
cold snap or a cold front comes through
she'll go in early and swap out and put
sweaters and stuff out in the store so
that you know she's like so reactive to
whatever is influencing the buyer that
day like from a day-to-day basis I'm
such a sucker for that like every
sweater I've ever bought I think was
because I was cold at a
store yeah it's so so smart um but what
I what I've learned one of the big
takeaways and I kind of knew this was
going to be an issue going in but didn't
put enough weight on it when you're
selling a business that is in a very I
would consider this to be the most Prime
retail space in this area probably in a
tri count area just because of like the
nature of who lives around it um the
landlord just has all of the leverage
and the buyers that we were we were deep
into a deal with like such a a stretched
out long period of time because the
buyers were relocating here so they
wanted to close on their business and
the building or their B business and
their house at the same time oh so yeah
we had this like four or five month deal
process and like we were like trying to
coordinate everything trying to like
synchronize all of this uh you know the
deal the due diligence them looking at a
house all this stuff um they were coming
from a different area and they were
trying to kind of bullishly negotiate
the
lease and and I was like you're just
like I was like at some point and I was
like I was like look this is like day
one day one of negotiating leas I was
like look I'm going to go to bat for you
I think you you have the right to
negotiate whatever you want to negotiate
I'm just the middleman here I'm GNA help
you but but be aware that you will get
to a point where they just say no yeah
and and if they say no like if you have
to understand if they needed to rent
this space it would never go to market
yes they would think that they wanted to
rent it and all of a sudden five people
would call like there's I'm sure there's
a waiting list right now for a space to
open up in this area so it's like they
don't have to bend and the amount that
this that this landlord bent on their
terms is insane really like so much so
they um you know they they wanted double
the that mean this business has been
there for 25 years so they want two
months security instead of one month
like they did 25 years ago fine yes yeah
but it's like seven Grand I mean and a
and a very profitable business is going
to do almost half a million like it's
but um yeah they like the landlord
agreed to do they wanted two months
still but they were going to give one
month back after a year so like they
were willing to negotiate on things yeah
they they were so this is like crazy one
so the the lease the current lease for
the seller is going to go up this year
so it's going to go up by $2,000 the
current tenant is going to pay $2,000
more for the next 12 months okay at you
know coming up soon $2,000 more a month
yeah a month okay the landlord was
willing to extend this year's payment
amount to for the next year for the new
tenant coming in to get there to get
acclimated oh why they're basically just
loaning the money for no reason goodness
of their hearts no it's so crazy so um
we had a signed lease term sheet but not
a signed lease and today is Wednesday uh
so just for context um Friday is the end
of due diligence they were going to go
to market to see that process how do
they go and meet the line like meet the
look at the lines and meet the sellers
and all that stuff to buy clothes that
that all starts next week um so three
days before the end of due diligence
they were about to sign the lease and
saw that they had to Pur guarantee it
which is very normal in Florida yeah
very standard you know llc's don't exist
they're a fake thing so most people
require you to to personally guarantee a
lease and yeah they said no and because
of how I wrote the LOI and this is why
you know you should talk to an attorney
and I shouldn't pretend to be one I've
nevere oh James cut that cut cut
cut I've never pretended to be a
um leave that in that's it yeah yeah I
don't care I you can't disbar me I'm
fake no I've never practiced law without
a license but I have provided templates
that I should not and cannot advise upon
and people should seek advice but they
don't always do it and on this template
that I provided that I did not provide
legal advice on it included a term under
due diligence that part of the
contingency for diligence was that we
had a lease agreement in place executed
lease agreement from now on I think I'm
going to say that we have executed lease
terms or there's probably a better way
to do this um but because of that one
sentence like we were're going to return
escrow they had every right to in
diligence because the lease was one of
the terms of diligence oh my God there's
so many things here it's just like the
landlord thing I'm always calling out
and everyone thinks I'm crazy but it
comes up so much and then you're
hammering the drum that I love of like
the LOI can shoot you in the foot um but
now I'm thinking I don't do this you
know my whole like thesis is put
everything in the
LOI um and uh I don't say anything about
the personal guarantee on the lease and
I could I could put in there including a
personal guarantee if required by the
landlord you know yeah but I'm writing
it from the buyer side so I'm usually
trying to keep more information out of
there but if I'm reviewing it from the
seller side I would probably start I'm
learning from this this is interesting
so is the deal dead in the water it's
dead yeah fully de sometimes the
landlord will let you not have the next
guy and personally guarantee it if your
person stayed on as a personal guarantor
yeah then they don't want to do that I
get that I wouldn't want to either and I
even talk to a mentor that's been
selling businesses for 30 years and he's
like every deal is going to have a
personal guarante he's like the only
ones that don't are rest and the
restaurante is like Savvy and they come
in and they say hey we'll pay a year in
advance with six months of security
deposit so that they don't have to
personally guarantee it in the SBA loan
is there a loan in this was there a loan
no it's cash what a bummer um SBA loan
really messes with the landlord
negotiation because they um require it
to fund so any Savvy landlord I try to
like really it took me a while to
realize like the angle of the landlord
in this is like what is their motivation
um in any deal to swap somebody out like
they have very little motivation to do
that um so everybody always says I have
a great relationship with a landlord it
won't be a problem and you're
like I will never die like that's and
that's what they said like that's what
they straight up said multiple times in
the negotiation is like we have a tenant
it's paying on time why do we care right
you have a tenant who's personally
guaranteed it who's paying stay on time
who's a known quantity and you're going
to let them off the hook and let some
unknown person with a brand new business
that might completely tank it on the
hook like why would you do that so now
we have a situation because there's one
more year on this lease yeah they very
well could say hey we don't want to
extend your lease because we know you're
trying to sell right I mean we've got to
find another deal I mean we will and
it's like such a good business I mean my
wife wants it so maybe we buy it do you
not love her buy her a boutique
I mean we did talk about it we actually
we had that conversation when the deal
fell through last night she was like do
you want to stay home with the kids
like and I was like you know and we're
just gonna end this early like Ian
Daniel's going yeah Daniel's be stay at
home Dad and uh podcast get like there's
just Cheerios that are thr at you I
wouldn't be the first person to have a
podcast that was pretending to do
something I did not do
[Laughter]
um no no it's uh I was like no you you'd
have you couldn't I mean my kids are
great but she works so much harder she
works so much harder than I do one day
it'll be easier and I I could be a
stay-at-home dad and she could run a
clothing the thing about the time like
I'm I'm at that c where you're like I
could do that because I got through you
know and that's about the time they're
in
school a great time to put your job yeah
two two or three more years once I'm at
your stage then um yeah I'll quit I'll
quit and work you know I'll be stay home
down anyway it's a great business and
she you know it's a it's a cool
lifestyle business I think for somebody
like you're on Ocean Drive with like
Galleries and great restaurants all
around you and a ton of cash flow and I
kind of want this
now you have to personally guarantee the
lease you person would you have to
personally guarantee every leas why
would you not do that like right to be
fair see so many leases I've seen
hundreds of leases in the m&a context in
the last couple years alone so like
relatively up to spe and I am saying you
always have to personally guarantee the
lease but that's not true a lot of
people will just have like a nons Savvy
landlord who's just a guy you know I
have one right now who only corresponds
by written mail um so we sent him a
lease assignment in the mail without a
cover letter even it just was like and I
don't have like a I don't send a lot of
mail I have I'll use the like docy post
to like go buy a stamp to send this yeah
so I have to like hand address it it's
like Mr so and
so so it doesn't always look them you
know like I guess I could get like
labels and stuff but that feels like a
lot of work so anyways received it back
signed this assignment and there's no
personal guarantee or anything um so
that's nice but and it happens sometimes
but it's very rare and almost not
desirable because you want like to lease
in a space where they're going to be
professional and um not screw you over
and they're going to take good care of
the property and usually that's going to
be a bigger company and then if you're
getting in so I try to flag the lease
thing like on every single call I'm like
a primary care physician who's like
thought about quit quitting smoking you
know like like they're like shut it like
I'm I got it like stop giving me
pamphlets on the lease thing but because
it tanks so many deals and it's like
their motivation is none and if you wait
until the point where they have this
like Pinnacle amount of negotiating
power the landlord does because they
know that if they say no the deal falls
through like that is not your best
interest it's much easier to negotiate
with them when it's like hey I might do
this I don't know I don't have a lot of
money invested in it either way can you
sign some stuff um versus when it's this
fever pitch and then with SBA they make
um the landlords sign this huge um kind
of I'll call it a subordination
agreement that says they have no rights
against any of the assets and that the
bank has all the rights and it has some
pretty aggressive terms in there like
that are just completely non-negotiable
like that and the landlord won't um take
the space back for 30 days because
they'll give the the bank like the right
to come in and collect stuff so um
landlords do not like to sign those
documents and so getting them in front
of them really
soon so and then a lot of times they're
really intimidating too so they think oh
God now I have to hire a lawyer so
you're making the landlord do all this
work andur all this cost for no benefit
to them um it's it's a favor you're
asking them like a big Financial favor
that's the double-edged sword to it when
you're sell especially when you're
selling in a prime area because you want
to buy a business in a prime area but
when you're in a prime area the landlord
not only has the leverage of the deal
but they have the leverage of the space
like they they know they just aren't
worried do you think you could negotiate
something like deals could bifurcate a
little bit where it when the space is so
important like in that context where
just a lum sum payment goes to the
landlord if the deal goes through yeah
for sure and I think that that's
something people should probably
consider like if we were going to start
to like put together some like Lessons
Learned and red flags to look out for
from this particular situation I would
say that if you're committed to doing an
asset sale as a buyer so if you're a
buyer you're doing an asset sale the
benefit to you is that you can
depreciate the assets that you buy so
it's tax advantaged for you but that has
cost so you know if you were to do a
stock sale alternatively where you're
buying the business as it exist
including its liabilities its contracts
and everything you can just walk right
in and you don't have to worry about it
but you give up that tax
benefit um there there's exceptions but
you know whatever um see me later we'll
talk about exceptions
um but if you were going to do an asset
sale and take advantage of that tax
benefit you may want to plan on offering
a little bit more money on rent to
sweeten the deal or you know like some
kind of a payment something something to
make the landlord not be an impediment
to the deal so so funny the way you said
that was such a such an accountant view
like the reason you do an asset sale in
my world is to limit your liability not
to depreciate the assets as much and
then um the stock
the caveat is a lot of times leases good
leases are written such that there if
there's a change of control of the
company even if it's a stock buyout it
still triggers um this requirement to
get land consent that's true because you
have the personal guarantee on almost
every lease in a commercial space So
yeah so even a stock sale you do still
have to transfer the personal guarantee
a lot of times landlords that are
stickier will let you add a personal
guarantor but not remove so you can stay
on as the seller knowing that they also
have the new person on there and then um
you have to just hang out until the end
of the lease for them to roll you off
and then sometimes if there's really big
company like a big platform company
they'll offer a parent guarantee instead
so like a different company that has
more assets will guarantee it instead of
an individual now if a seller does do a
stock sale and they have to stay on as a
personal guarantor for the rest of a
lease in this case it's one year so it's
not that big of a deal but if it like
let's say it is three or four years
should they require some of the purchase
proceeds to what should they do like how
can they secure themselves you get some
serious um specific indemnification
language in there so personal guarantees
are typically joint and several um which
is a thing you hear a lot um and don't
really know what it means but what it
means is if there's two people on the
hook for something the person can go
after either one for 100% of the issue
and they don't have to go after them
equally for 50% and they don't have to
go after one first so in reality what
people just go after the person who
seems like they have the most assets so
yeah you know I always advise my clients
of that because sometimes there'll be a
room of four people and they're all equ
you know joint and severally liable but
I say is there any one of you that you
know seems like they're a lot richer and
there's like one guy and like they're
going after you man like I don't know to
tell you um and I think that's important
to know so you're selling and the buyer
seems like they have a lot more going on
but also if the buyer is defaulting you
can imagine they don't have any assets
so they're probably gonna go after the
seller personal guarantee then you get
the indemnification um stuff but you're
still in a situation where that person
has no assets typically if they're
defaulting on a lease so like what are
you gonna do about it um it's not an
ideal uh thing to be dealing with but at
the same time if it gets the deal done
and it's for a short period of time um I
have negotiated The Joint in several
language so that's not always the case
you can say yeah yeah yeah we'll stay on
but we're gonna add language that says
you'll go after this guy first at least
you know admittedly if you're listening
to this you know that I'm I'm not
pretending to be some veteran here I'm
new to this new to this uh business
brokerage World um but it's such a
tricky thing to deal with and I I have
talked to people who have been buying
and selling businesses for 20 30 years
and it never gets any easier but the um
letting the landlord know about the deal
is almost always what breaches
confidentiality yeah so you want it to
happen later so you don't compromise the
business but the later you do it the
more power they have in tanking the deal
what are you going to do like you maybe
you get them to sign NDA if you're lucky
but then like you can't sue them because
then you lose the space anyway I get why
people say I have a great relationship
with landlord even though that's
completely absurd because I hear it so
often and it doesn't pan out that way at
all um but it is good to try to have a
great relationship with the landlord so
that they're willing to play ball when
that kind of thing happens and I think
um maybe the the one thing to distill
from this interaction and this like bad
outcome which I'm just hearing about for
the first time so sorry that that
happened is um that you should not
overestimate your negotiating power when
it comes to a landlord because like you
have none
so um be collegial be you know willing
to um sometimes they'll even require
like your spouse to personally guarantee
release I'm dealing with that right now
and the person says is this reasonable
yeah in case somebody passed away or
something or in case people get clever I
don't know how many clients have said to
me I've got a great idea I'm gonna put
all my Assets in my spouse's name or I
I'm G to be a women-owned small business
um and get all those government cont
contracts by putting it my whole
business in my 18-year-old daughter's
name like that's great that's people
have thought about that they've tried
they've tried this before so you're not
the first one lessons and red
flags I think for
me I don't have a great lesson for
anybody to share I'm sorry on when you
should talk about lease whether it's
early in due diligence or late in due
diligence but like there's got to like
you got to weigh it out based on the
experience if you're a seller
again you know depends on your
relationship you know it's it's probably
better to know where you stand if you're
going to sell yeah so a lease especially
a lease that's not drafted by competent
legal counsel it could be good or it
could be bad like it could be great if
you have a nice formal well draw drawn
out lease that includes Provisions for
if you were to sell the business but it
may also be more limiting whereas if you
have you know back of the napkin lease
it may be easier to get away with stuff
but but you're also going to be uh you
know have greater liabilities so I'm
going to admit I'm out of my depth on
this one it's a learning experience for
me Sarah do you have uh some lessons
from your experience or red flags people
could watch out for to take away from
this and how to make this not a deal
killer I mean just that's what I'm
always trying to hammer is be afraid be
very afraid of the landlord because it's
a you can't make them do anything it's
like employees you can't force anyone to
come work with you and the seller can't
force anyone to know lease you the space
or come work with you so since the two
parties of the deal can't control it you
you really have to use all the possible
EQ but yeah I think if you're the seller
building in some kind of reason some
kind of motivation for the the landlord
to move forward even if it's just a
conversation where you say this is like
this is the reason I trust this person
is a buyer to pay me for probably years
to come I would not into this deal if I
thought they were going to be anything
but great to you and your space so there
we go I think that's great advice don't
lose a deal like I did a couple weeks
out from closing talk to the landlord
incentivize them just pay them off
greasing Palms is always the answer old
school corruption yeah yeah case full of
cash Park yeah that's that's how
businesses are bought and sold still old
school still GRE have to go right now to
a park with this Briefcase full of cash
I'm kidding don't just the brief Cade of
cash briefcase of cash or a baseball bat
right get the deal done this has been
episode 17 if you got any value from
this please like subscribe and follow us
on the social media platforms uh comment
if you have any questions you'd like for
us to
[Music]
answer do it bigger than anybody